export const ECONOMICSA2019 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. The fundamental economic problem in every society is",
A: "the large number of the unemployed.",
B: "inadequate supply of money.",
C: "limited supply of productive resources.",
D: "corruption and mismanagement.",
answer: "C. limited supply of productive resources.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. A point X inside a production possibility curve indicates that",
A: "resources are fully utilized.",
B: "the country is poor.",
C: "resources are not available.",
D: "some resources are idle.",
answer: "D. some resources are idle.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. The major employer of labour in developing countries is",
A: "tertiary sector.",
B: "primary sector.",
C: "secondary sector.",
D: "industrial sector.",
answer: "B. primary sector.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. The desire for profit is a major feature of",
A: "traditional economy.",
B: "Mixed economy.",
C: "command economy.",
D: "market economy.",
answer: "D. market economy.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. The wages of a group of workers in dollars ate stated below:  40, 30, 70, 20, 60, 10, 10, 80, 30 and 10.  What is the mean wage?",
A: "$36",
B: "$35",
C: "$37",
D: "$38",
answer: "A. $36",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. If the coefficient of price elasticity of demand of a product is zero, then its demand curve will be",
A: "parallel to the price axis.",
B: "parallel to the quantity axis.",
C: "negatively sloped.",
D: "positively sloped.",
answer: "A. parallel to the price axis.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. If the demand function is Qd = -0.5p + 20, calculate the quantity demand when price is $15.00.",
A: "-$12.50",
B: "-$27.50",
C: "$27.50",
D: "$12.50",
answer: "D. $12.50",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. If less of a good is bought as one’s income increases, such good is:",
A: "an inferior good.",
B: "a luxury good.",
C: "a necessity.",
D: "a normal good.",
answer: "A. an inferior good.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. The demand for coffee and tea is",
A: "joint.",
B: "derived.",
C: "composite.",
D: "competitive.",
answer: "D. competitive.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. What effect will an increase in the supply of fish have on the meat market?",
A: "An increase in equilibrium price and fall in quantity.",
B: "An increase in equilibrium price and quantity.",
C: "A fall in equilibrium price and quantity.",
D: "Both equilibrium price and quantity remain unchanged",
answer: "C. A fall in equilibrium price and quantity.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Which of the following factors is not a condition for change in supply of a commodity?",
A: "Improved technology.",
B: "Cost of production.",
C: "Government tax policy.",
D: "The price of the commodity.",
answer: "D. The price of the commodity.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. Supply of agricultural products is likely to be elastic in the",
A: "intermediate period.",
B: "short-run.",
C: "long-run.",
D: "market period.",
answer: "C. long-run.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. Two commodities X and Y are in joint supply when",
A: "An increase in X leads to a decrease in Y.",
B: "X and Y are produced by the same firm.",
C: "X is a by-product of Y.",
D: "X and Y cannot be produced in the same process.",
answer: "C. X is a by-product of Y.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. The table above illustrates the law of",
A: "diminishing returns.",
B: "diminishing marginal productivity.",
C: "variable proportion.",
D: "diminishing marginal utility.",
answer: "D. diminishing marginal utility.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. When the price of a good is above the equilibrium, there will be",
A: "a surplus.",
B: "a shortage.",
C: "unemployment.",
D: "inflation.",
answer: "A. a surplus.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. What happens when a minimum price is imposed in a market?",
A: "Short occurs.",
B: "The market maintains the equilibrium.",
C: "Surplus occurs.",
D: "Many firms will close down.",
answer: "C. Surplus occurs.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. When an increase in inputs leads to a more than proportionate increase in output, there is",
A: "decreasing returns to scale.",
B: "increasing returns to scale.",
C: "increase in marginal products.",
D: "constant returns to scale.",
answer: "B. increasing returns to scale.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. The short-run in production is the time period when",
A: "Techniques of production can easily be changed.",
B: "All factors of production are variable.",
C: "Variable factors cannot be changed.",
D: "At least a factor is fixed while others are variable.",
answer: "D. At least a factor is fixed while others are variable",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. Calculate the value of Q.",
A: "$350",
B: "$360",
C: "$340",
D: "$370",
answer: "B. $36",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. A cost of production that is positively related to output is the",
A: "total fixed cost.",
B: "variable cost.",
C: "average fixed cost.",
D: "social cost.",
answer: "B. variable cost",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. In perfect competition, the average revenue curve is",
A: "below the marginal revenue curve.",
B: "downward sloping.",
C: "convex the origin.",
D: "the marginal revenue curves",
answer: "D. the marginal revenue curves.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Which of the following means of funding a business is very reliable and cheap?",
A: "Bank loans",
B: "Plough back profit",
C: "Loans from friends",
D: "Debentures",
answer: "D. Debentures",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. Government in most cases influences location of firms to",
A: "discourage private investors.",
B: "make firms enjoy economics of scale.",
C: "reduce cost of production.",
D: "ensure fair distribution.",
answer: "B. make firms enjoy economics of scale.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. Middlemen are made up of",
A: "manufacturers, wholesalers and consumers.",
B: "Wholesalers, retailers and hawkers.",
C: "manufacturers, wholesalers and retailers.",
D: "wholesalers, retailers and consumers.",
answer: "B. Wholesalers, retailers and hawkers.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. The Malthusian theory of population was proved wrong because",
A: "new lands and new methods of production were discovered.",
B: "developing countries adopted birth control methods.",
C: "the practice of subsistence farming was encouraged.",
D: "Malthus’ view was seen as an exaggeration",
answer: "A. new lands and new methods of production were discovered.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. Human development can be improved",
A: "if banks give more loans to businessmen.",
B: "large family sizes are encouraged.",
C: "it is handled by the private sector only.",
D: "general education and training are encouraged.",
answer: "D. general education and training are encouraged.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. The use of interest rates to control money supply is a",
A: "monetary policy.",
B: "control policy.",
C: "development policy.",
D: "fiscal policy.",
answer: "A. monetary policy.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. Agricultural productivity may be increased if",
A: "educational institutions are established in rural areas.",
B: "commercial banks are established in rural areas.",
C: "labour intensive methods of agriculture is encouraged.",
D: "more infrastructural facilities are provided in rural areas.",
answer: "D. more infrastructural facilities are provided in rural areas.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. A country is described as industrialized if",
A: "traditional and modern sectors coexist.",
B: "the contribution of industries to national income is high.",
C: "the country adopts import promotion strategy.",
D: "primary industries dominate the economy.",
answer: "B. the contribution of industries to national income is high.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. Which of the following is a major advantage of establishing a tomato processing factory in your country?",
A: "Foreign exchange will be conserved",
B: "More unskilled labour will be employed",
C: "Local consumption will decrease",
D: "It will attract more tourists",
answer: "A. Foreign exchange will be conserved",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. The total value of goods and services produced within the borders of a country is",
A: "net domestic product.",
B: "gross domestic product.",
C: "net national product.",
D: "gross national product.",
answer: "B. gross domestic product.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. Which of the following items is not considered as a transfer payment?",
A: "Pension pay",
B: "Government subsidy",
C: "Doctor’s salary",
D: "Student’s grant",
answer: "C. Doctor’s salary",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. Which of the following factors will not underestimate the national income?",
A: "Rapid decrease in price",
B: "Increased subsistence production",
C: "Increase in value of services not paid for",
D: "Practice of specialization of labour.",
answer: "D. Practice of specialization of labour.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Which of the following is true of the value of money? It",
A: "is positively related to the price level.",
B: "is inversely related to the price level.",
C: "is determined by the government.",
D: "depends on the value people attach to it.",
answer: "B. is inversely related to the price level.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. The motive for holding money to mccl unforeseen events is termed",
A: "liquidity demand.",
B: "transactions demand.",
C: "precautionary demand.",
D: "speculative demand.",
answer: "C. precautionary demand.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. An increase in the prices of factor inputs may result in",
A: "cost-push inflation.",
B: "stagflation.",
C: "demand-pull inflation.",
D: "open inflation.",
answer: "A. cost-push inflation.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Insurance companies are similar to commercial banks in that they",
A: "compensate the customers for losses.",
B: "help in mobilizing savings for investment.",
C: "help in maintaining monetary stability in a nation",
D: "act as lender of last resort.",
answer: "B. help in mobilizing savings for investment.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. What happens when the central bank increases the bank rate?",
A: "Amount of borrowing increases",
B: "Commercial banks are not affected",
C: "Supply of money increases",
D: "Amount of borrowing decreases",
answer: "D. Amount of borrowing decreases",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. Citizens are protected from government’s arbitrariness in taxation by the canon of",
A: "elasticity.",
B: "flexibility.",
C: "certainty.",
D: "economy.",
answer: "C. certainty.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. In a period of unemployment and falling prices. government should adopt a",
A: "zero budget deficit.",
B: "zero-based budget.",
C: "balanced budget.",
D: "surplus budget.",
answer: "B. zero-based budget.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. In most developing countries a large percentage of the labour force engaged in",
A: "trading",
B: "agriculture.",
C: "construction.",
D: "manufacturing.",
answer: "B. agriculture.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. In most underdeveloped countries, development plans do not achieve their objectives due to",
A: "lack of education institutions in those countries.",
B: "exportation of more primary products.",
C: "poor coordination between local and national government.",
D: "urban rural migration of citizens.",
answer: "C. poor coordination between local and national government.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. Balance of trade involves exchange of",
A: "goods and capital.",
B: "services only.",
C: "goods and services.",
D: "goods only.",
answer: "C. goods and services.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. An improvement in a country’s terms of trade means that the",
A: "value of her imports is lower than her exports.",
B: "nation’s receipts on export is equal to payments on imports.",
C: "nation can export more services.",
D: "visible exports is less than visible imports.",
answer: "A. value of her imports is lower than her exports.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. Devaluation of currency may not correct a balance of payment deficit if the demand for export is",
A: "fairly elastic.",
B: "perfectly elastic.",
C: "perfectly inelastic.",
D: "unitary elastic.",
answer: "C. perfectly inelastic.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. One measure of financing a country’s balance of payments deficit is through",
A: "export diversification.",
B: "import substitution.",
C: "internal borrowing from commercial banks.",
D: "short-term borrowing from IMF.",
answer: "D. short-term borrowing from IMF.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. The major Achievement of the Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS) is that it has",
A: "made capital more mobile.",
B: "made possible the use of common currency.",
C: "widened the market for goods produced.",
D: "increased members’ allegiance to former colonial masters.",
answer: "C. widened the market for goods produced.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. Which of the following institutions is concerned with expanding developing countries’ commodity trade?",
A: "United Nations Conference on Trade and Development (UNCTAD)",
B: "World Trade Organization (WTO)",
C: "Economic Commission for Africa (ECA)",
D: "African Development Bank (AfDB)",
answer: "A. United Nations Conference on Trade and Development (UNCTAD)",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. Exploitation of forest resources becomes a major problem when”",
A: "communities fight over ownership.",
B: "they are neglected.",
C: "they are not renewed.",
D: "the supply is fixed in the long-run.",
answer: "C. they are not renewed.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. Natural resources that are renewable are found in the",
A: "agricultural sector.",
B: "traditional sector.",
C: "mining sector.",
D: "secondary sector.",
answer: "A. agricultural sector.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},


]